Guide to the South Africa Documentary Photographs Collection, 1940s-2007 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
South Africa Documentary Collection photographs 1940s-2007 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harris, Alex.
48.5 linear feet Extent: Approx. 1098 Items
Alex Harris is a documentary photographer who co-founded the series of South African documentary projects represented in part by the works in this collection. The South Africa Documentary Photographs Collection consists of four series of 1,035 photographic images documenting South African social conditions under and after apartheid, dating from approximately the 1940s-2007: Beyond the Barricades, The Cordoned Heart, Then and Now, and Underexposed. Each series originated in an exhibition, book, or project developed jointly by Duke University and South African institutions. The collection represents the work of 44 South African photographers, many of whom were members of Afrapix, a collective photography agency that was politically active in the 1980s, or active in documenting anti-apartheid struggle. The fourth series, "Underexposed," includes older photographs dating from the 1940s and 1950s, with a focus on photographers considered less well-known at the time. The images take the form of black-and-white and color prints, chiefly gelatin silver and pigmented inkjet prints, ranging in size from 5x7 inch reference prints to 16x20 inch finished prints. There is a small amount of printed materials, and digital versions of some of the images. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
RL.01129
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The prints and other materials in the South Africa Documentary Photographs Collection were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts from 1993-2010.
Biographical Notes on Photographers in the Collection
Paul Alberts (1946- )
Alberts is a Cape Town freelance photojournalist who has served as arts editor for Die Burger magazine. He is founder and director of The Gallery Press. He has published photographs in major magazines and four photography books.
Joseph Alphers (1949- )
Alphers has worked as a commercial photographer, a photojournalist, and a photographer for the University of Bophuthatswana. He was an Afrapix member. His work dates from the 1970s.
Omar Badsha (1945- )
Badsha is a self-taught painter and photographer who became active as a photographer in the mid-1970s. He was an anti-apartheid activist, a labor organizer, and a founding member of Afrapix, as well as an editor of South Africa: The Cordoned Heart. He has published four books of photography, including one banned in South Africa, and manages the South African History Online project.
Rodney Barnett (1943-2000)
Barnett photographed in Johannesburg, elsewhere in Africa, and during world travels. He published several works of photography, and was a founder of South Africa's South Photographic Agency.
Michael Barry (1954- )
Barry spent a year as supervisor of The Haven Night Shelter in Cape Town, the site of some of his photographs. He has taught art in a Port Elizabeth high school, and was a member of the art collective Vukalisa.
Bee Berman (1949- )
Berman became a freelance news photographer in 1980. Her photographs have appeared in exhibitions and books in South Africa and elsewhere.
Arthur Bolton
Arthur Bolton was a British radiologist who settled in KwaZulu Natal after the Second World War. He was a keen photographer whose work is predominantly about Zulu culture in the field as well as in the studio.
Basil Breakey
Basil Breakey's work focuses on South African jazz culture. He is best known for his photographs in Beyond The Blues: Township Jazz in the 1960s and 1970s.
Julian Cobbing (1944- )
Cobbing is a British historian of African history who has taught at Rhodes University in South Africa. He is known for his research on Zulu culture of the early 19th century.
Michael Davies (1955- )
Davies is a photographer and sculptor. As a photographer, he is known for his images of South African political struggle primarily from the 1980s. His work has been exhibited in South African group exhibitions.
Gille de Vlieg (1940- )
De Vlieg was born in England and emigrated to South Africa. She was a member of both the Black Sash movement and Afrapix. Her photographs of apartheid resistance and life under apartheid date from the 1980s.
Anne Fischer (1915-1986)
Fischer was a commercial studio photographer specializing in portraits. Her personal projects photographing rural South Africans date from approximately the 1940s.
David Goldblatt (1930- )
Goldblatt became a full-time photographer in 1963. He has worked as photography director and associate editor for Leadership S.A.. His photographs are held by numerous institutions, including the Bibliotheque Nationale, Paris; the Museum of Modern Art, New York; and the South African National Gallery, Cape Town. He was the founder of the Market Photography Workshop in Johannesburg.
Jenny Gordon (1955- )
Gordon became a freelance photojournalist in the 1980s. She also specializes in portraiture. She was the director of the Market Photography Workshop in Johannesburg. Her photographs have been exhibited internationally and have been published in numerous books and periodicals.
Paul Grendon (1954- )
Grendon is a painter, curator, and freelance photographer whose photographic work dates from the 1980s. He was a member of Afrapix. His work has been exhibited in numerous venues.
George Hallett (1942- )
In the 1960s, Hallett photographed District Six in Cape Town before the neighborhood's destruction under apartheid. Between 1970 and 1995 he left South Africa for Europe, where much of his work focused on South African artists in exile. In 1994 he was one of a group of photographers documenting the first democratic election in South Africa for the Independent Electoral Commission. He was later commissioned to record the work of the Truth and Reconciliation Commission.
Dave Hartman
Hartman was an Afrapix member who photographed apartheid resistance in the 1980s.
David Hemson
Hemson was a labor activist in Durban during the 1970s. He went on to become a sociologist and the research director of the Human Sciences Research Council in Durban.
Steve Hilton-Barber (1962-2002)
Hilton-Barber was a freelance journalist and a member of Afrapix. He was a founder of the SouthLight Photographic agency. During the 1990s he worked with several South African newspapers.
Paul Konings (1958- )
Konings was born in New Zealand and moved to Cape Town in 1975. He became a freelance photographer and graphic artist. His work dates from the 1970s, and has been included in several books.
Lesley Lawson (1952- )
Lawson has been a writer and photographer for the South African Council for Higher Education. She was a member of Afrapix. During the 1970s and 1980s her work focused on labor, women, and political activism; she later was moved to focus on HIV issues. She has published two books, one on working women and one on HIV.
Chris Ledechowski (1956- )
Ledechowski is a freelance photographer who has worked on various documentary projects in South Africa, in photography and film. He was a member of Afrapix. His photographs and hand-tinted portraits have been exhibited in South Africa.
Rashid Lombard (1951- )
Lombard has worked as a freelance photographer and photojournalist. He was a founder of the Cape Town Press Centre. He has been CEO of espAFRIKA, organizer of a major South African jazz festival. His work has been exhibited in a number of group exhibitions in South Africa. He was a member of the art collective Vukalisa.
Ben Maclennan (1956- )
Maclennan was born in Scotland and grew up in South Africa. He is a press photographer, reporter, and editor whose work dates from the 1970s. He has worked for the South African Press Association. He worked as photographer on the Surplus People Project in 1982. His photographs have been shown in African group exhibitions and were published in various works during the early 1980s.
Jimi Matthews (1955- )
Matthews has worked as a freelance photojournalist and cameraman for international television networks, and he has been a member of the art collective Vukalisa. His photographs have been exhibited internationally.
Roger Meintjies (1963- )
Roger Meintjes' documentary work dates from the 1980s, during which time he was a member of the Afrapix collective. In the 1990s he was employed at the Robben Island Museum. Meintjies' photographs have been published in a number of books and magazines.
Gideon Mendel (1959- )
Mendel is a photojournalist who has worked for Agence France Press Photo Service. His photographs have appeared in Time, The New York Times, and other major magazines and newspapers.
Eric Miller
Miller was a member of Afrapix. His work appeared in the Weekly Mail, the New Nation, and other progressive publications. Since 1994, Miller has photographed throughout Africa. Much of his South African work has focused on the transformation of society, especially in respect to housing, health, education, and labor. He has published a book on the Lord’s Resistance Army in Uganda.
Santu Mofokeng (1956- )
Mofokeng freelanced through the Afrapix Photographers Collective, and has taught at the Institute for Advanced Social Research at the University of Witwatersrand. His work has been exhibited in South Africa and at the Guggenheim Museum. He received the Mother Jones International Fund for Documentary Photography Award in 1996.
Daniel Morolong
Morolong was a press photographer covering social events in East London. His work dates from the 1950s and was exhibited in East London in 2003.
Themba Nkosi
[No biographical information is currently available for Nkosi.]
Cedric Nunn (1957- )
Nunn's photographs date from 1981, when he began documenting apartheid issues. His photographs focused especially on rural areas. He was a founding member of Afrapix. In 1994 he was one of a group of photographers documenting the first democratic election in South Africa for the Independent Electoral Commission.
Billy Paddock
Paddock was a journalist who was active in the End Conscription Campaign, and he was a member of Afrapix. in 1982 he was imprisoned for a year for refusing military conscription. Paddock died in the early 1990s.
Berney Perez (1948- )
Perez is a freelance photographer. His work has been exhibited in group exhibitions in South Africa and elsewhere.
Myron Peters (1954- )
Peters was active in the Black Conciousness Movement and the Natal Indian Congress. While a student, he was an associate member of Afrapix. His photographs appeared in group exhibitions in South Africa and in a number of books. Peters went on to receive a Masters in Development Studies and worked in the South African government.
Chris Qwazi
Qwazi is a photographer whose work dates from the 1980s. His work has covered anti-apartheid struggle and has been exhibited in South Africa.
Jeeva Rajgopaul (1952- )
Rajgopaul is a freelance documentary photographer. He was a member of Afrapix. He has been awarded the Earnest Cole Scholarship for Documentary Photography.
Wendy Schwegmann (1954- )
Schwegmann was a freelance photojournalist working for Reuters in South Africa in the 1970s and 1980s, and was a member of Afrapix. Her photographs are held in the South African National Gallery. Schwegmann went on to work for Reuters in London.
Guy Tillim (1962- )
Tillim began photographing professionally in 1986, and was a member of Afrapix. Since the 1990s, he has photographed throughout Africa and the world, often in war-torn areas. His work has received numerous awards, including the South African Mondi award for photojournalism, the Higashikawa Overseas Photographer Award, the Daimler Chrysler Award for South African Photography, and the Leica Oskar Barnack Award.
Zubeida Vallie
Vallie was a member of Afrapix. She documented anti-apartheid struggle in the 1980s.
Paul Weinberg (1956- )
Weinberg has been photographing professionally since 1978 and was a founder of the collective Afrapix. In addition to his own work which examines people, cultures, and human environments, he has photographed on assignment for newspapers, magazines, and non-governmental organizations. In 1993, Weinberg won a Mother Jones International Fund for Documentary Photography Award. He is the Curator at the Centre for Curating the Archive at the University of Cape Town and was instrumental in supporting the series of projects represented in part by the photographic work in this collection.
Graeme Williams (1961- )
Williams is a freelance photographer who works on documentary projects and magazine photography. Beginning in 1988, he worked for Reuters covering the resistance to apartheid and the movement toward African National Congress rule. His more recent color work focuses on the details of people’s lives as a means of exploring change and the lack of change in contemporary South African society. He has published a number of books.
Jansje Wissema (1920-1975)
Wissema was a pioneering woman photographer and documentary photographer. She was born in Holland and emigrated to South Africa. She is known for her published photographs of District Six in Cape Town before the neighborhood's destruction in the 1960s. Her work spans the 1940s through the 1970s.
Gisèle Wulfsohn (1957- )
Wulfson is a freelance photographer. In the early 1980s, she worked for the Star newspaper and Style magazine. She was a member of Afrapix. In 1994, she was among the photographers commissioned by the Independent Electoral Commission (IEC) to document the first democratic elections in South Africa. She is primarily concerned with gender issues, education, and health. She has been documenting the manifestations of HIV/AIDS in South Africa since the late 1980s.
Collection Overview
The South Africa Documentary Photographs Collection consists of four series of 1,035 photographs documenting South African social conditions during and after apartheid, dating from approximately 1940 to 2007: Beyond the Barricades, The Cordoned Heart, Then and Now, and Underexposed. Each series originated in an exhibition, book, or project developed jointly by the Duke University Center for Documentary Studies and South African institutions such as the Centre for Curating the Archive at the University of Cape Town. The collection represents the work of 44 South African photographers, many of whom were members of Afrapix, a collective photography agency that was politically active in the 1980s, or were otherwise active in documenting anti-apartheid struggle.
Among the names in this collection are several documentary photographers whose individual bodies of work are also held at Duke: Alex Harris, David Goldblatt, Cedric Nunn, and Paul Weinberg. All photographers are described in a biographical section above, and they are listed in each series description below. Images consist of rural and urban South African scenes; images of events such as rallies, protests, forced removals, funerals, social gatherings, and labor activities; and portraits of individuals, including some well-known activists and politicians, men and women.
The images take the form of black-and-white and color prints, chiefly gelatin silver and pigmented inkjet prints, ranging in size from 5x7 inch reference prints to 16x20 inch finished prints, with some in museum-quality mats. There is a small amount of textual material documenting the photographs and their earlier exhibition. Many of the photographs are also available as digital images mounted on the library server; please contact a reference archivist for access. There is one digital audio file documenting an exhibit opening for Then and Now at Duke University, also available on the library server.
The Beyond the Barricades Series consists of 82 unmatted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints dating from 1980 to 1988. The photographs were taken as part of a project initiated by the collective photo agency Afrapix, which documented anti-apartheid struggle in the 1980s. Events portrayed include funerals, conflicts with police, rallies and demonstrations, and other political gatherings. Individuals appearing in the photographs include Chief Buthelezi, Archbishop Desmond Tutu, President P.W. Botha, and activists such as Billy Nair. Numerous anti-apartheid organizations are also represented in the images. The photographs in this series were published in the book Beyond the Barricades: Popular Resistance in South Africa (1989), and appeared in an accompanying exhibit.
The Cordoned Heart Series houses 191 gelatin silver prints, the bulk dating from between 1979 and 1984, taken by twenty South African photographers. There are both matted and unmatted prints. The series documents a crucial period of protest and social upheaval in South African history, focusing on poverty and the daily lives of people living under apartheid. Textual materials from the exhibit South Africa: The Cordoned Heart, which appeared originally at the International Center of Photography in 1986, are also housed in this series; they include exhibit brochures and an exhibit installation guide.
The Then and Now Series consists of 160 prints taken by eight South African photographer sdocumenting South Africa before and after apartheid, ranging in date from 1963 to 2006. The series originated in a 2008 exhibition at Duke University curated by South African photographer Paul Weinberg, entitled "Then and Now: Eight South African Photographers. The exhibit comprised ten photographs from each photographer covering the period of apartheid and ten from the period following democratic elections in 1994. All of the images are available in an online exhibit. The series also contains a digitized audio file recorded at the exhibition's opening, also available through the online exhibit page.
The final series, Underexposed, is comprised of 602 prints documenting the work of eleven South African photographers. Prints are pigmented inkjet, gelatin silver, and color, with dates ranging from approximately the 1950s to 2007. The series originated in a project of the Centre for Curating the Archive at the University of Cape Town. The project emphasized photographers considered relatively unknown and underexposed, hence the name of the project. The series includes a significant number of women photographers. Photographs depict a variety of subjects, including political protest, family life, leisure, portraits, rural and impoverished social conditions, and labor conditions.
Photographers whose work is represented in this collection are: Paul Alberts (1946- ); Joseph Alphers (1949- );Omar Badsha (1945- ); Rodney Barnett (1943-2000); Michael Barry (1954- ); Bee Berman (1949- ); Arthur Bolton; Basil Breakey; Julian Cobbing (1944- ); Michael Davies (1955- ); Gille de Vlieg (1940- ); Anne Fischer (1915-1986); David Goldblatt (1930- ); Jenny Gordon (1955- ); Paul Grendon (1954- ); George Hallett (1942- ); Dave Hartman; David Hemson; Steve Hilton-Barber (1962-2002); Paul Konings (1958-); Lesley Lawson (1952- ); Chris Ledechowski (1956- ); Rashid Lombard (1951- ); Ben Maclennan (1956- ); Jimi Matthews (1955- ); Roger Meintjies (1963- ); Gideon Mendel (1959- ); Eric Miller; Santu Mofokeng (1956- ); Daniel Morolong; Themba Nkosi; Cedric Nunn (1957- ); Billy Paddock; Berney Perez (1948- ); Myron Peters (1954- ); Chris Qwazi; Jeeva Rajgopaul (1952- ); Wendy Schwegmann (1954- ); Guy Tillim (1962- ); Zubeida Vallie; Paul Weinberg (1956- ); Graeme Williams (1961- ); Jansje Wissema (1920-1975); and Gisèle Wulfsohn (1957- ).
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Subject Headings
Goldblatt, David; Harris, Alex, 1949-; Nunn, Cedric; Weinberg, Paul; Afrapix; Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies; University of Cape Town. Centre for Curating the Archive; Anti-apartheid movements -- South Africa; Apartheid -- Africa; Apartheid -- South Africa; Documentary photography -- South Africa; Protest movements -- South Africa; South Africa -- Race relations; South Africa -- Pictorial works; South Africa -- Politics and government; South Africa -- Social conditions -- 1961-1994; CD-ROMs; Sound recordings; Machine-readable records; Photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Related Material
Harris, Alex and Iris Tillman Hill (eds.). Beyond the Barricades: Popular Resistance in South Africa. New York: Aperture, 1989.
Perkins/Bostock Library, Duke University
Alex Harris Photographs and Papers, 1970-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
David Goldblatt Photographs and Films, 1960-1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Paul Weinberg Photographs, 1979-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Then and Now: Eight South African Photographers
Duke Libraries Digital Collections
Weinberg, Paul (ed.). Then and Now: Eight South African Photographers. Johannesburg: Highveld Press, 2008.
Perkins/Bostock Library, Duke University
Wilson, Francis. South Africa: The Cordoned Heart. New York: W.W. Norton, 1986.
Perkins/Bostock Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Beyond the Barricades Series, 1981-1988, (2 boxes)
  Consists of 82 unmatted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints dating from 1981 to 1988. The photographers were South Africans who were primarily members of Afrapix, the collective photo agency that documented resistance to apartheid in the 1980s. The images originated with the Afrapix documentary project "Beyond the Barricades." The project resulted in an exhibit and a book, Beyond the Barricades: Popular Resistance in South Africa (1989), published in cooperation with the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University. Afrapix photographers Omar Badsha, Gideon Mendel, and Paul Weinberg selected photographs for the book.
  The photographs document social and political protest in South Africa during the 1980s; events include funerals, conflicts with police, rallies and demonstrations, and other political gatherings. Individuals appearing in the photographs include Chief Buthelezi, Archbishop Desmond Tutu, President P.W. Botha, and activists such as Billy Nair. Numerous anti-apartheid organizations are portrayed, including the African National Congress (ANC), the Congress of South African Trade Unions (COSATU), the Leandra Youth Congress, the Natal Indian Congress, and the United Democratic Front (UDF).
  The images were taken by twenty South African photographers: Omar Badsha, Julian Cobbing, Paul Grendon, Steve Hilton-Berber, Dave Hartman, Rashid Lombard, Roger Meintjies, Gideon Mendel, Eric Miller, Santu Mofokeng, Themba Nkosi, Cedric Nunn, Billy Paddock, Myron Peters, Chris Qwazi, Jeeva Rajgopaul, Guy Tillim, Zubeida Vallie, Gille de Vlieg, and Paul Weinberg. There are also six prints by unidentified photographers. The series is arranged alphabetically by photographer.
  Photographs are not dated or captioned. The bulk of the photographs are described in the book Beyond the Barricades. Many of the photographs are also available as digital images mounted on the library server; please contact a reference archivist for access.
  - Omar Badsha, 1981-1987, (15 prints) (Box 1)